Frank Stick Papers and Artwork PC.5089
Frank Stick Papers and Artwork
1910-1966 and undated
PC.5089
35.830
Frank Stick was an artist, conservationist, real estate developer, and writer active on the Outer Banks of North Carolina from the 1920s to the 1960s. The Frank Stick Papers and Artwork, 1910-1966 and undated, contains a substantial collection of artwork and personal papers created by Stick. Included in the collection are Stick's fish watercolors, several of his landscape and naturalist oil paintings, papers related to his family and personal life, documentation of his efforts to establish the Cape Hatteras National Seashore and Virgin Islands National Park, numerous deeds and other real estate records documenting the early development of the Outer Banks, plans for his signature flat top cottages, drafts of his writings, and papers related to members of his immediate family.
Stick, Frank
Outer Banks History Center
Box Box 1
Box Box 2
Box Box 3
Box Box 4
Box Box 10
Box Box 11
Box Box 5
Box Box 6
Box Box 7
Box Box 8
Box Box 9
Box Oversize Box 1
Box Oversize Box 2
Box Oversize Box 3
Box Oversize Box 4
Box Oversize Box 5
Box Oversize Box 6
Box Oversize Box 7
Box Oversize Box 8
Box Oversize Box 9
Box Oversize Box 10
Box Oversize Box 11
Box Oversize Box 12
Box Oversize Box 13
Box Oversize Box 14
Box Oversize Box 15
Box Oversize Box 16
Box Oversize Box 17
Box Oversize Box 18
Box Image Box 1
Box Image Box 2
Box Image Box 3
Box Image Box 4
Box Image Box 5
Box Image Box 6
Box Image Box 7
Box Image Box 8
Box Image Box 9
Box Image Box 10
Box Image Box 11
Box Image Box 12
Box Image Box 13
Box Image Box 14
Box Image Box 15
Box Image Box 16
Box Image Box 17
Box Image Box 18
Folder Oversize Folder 1
Box Long Key
Box Surf Off New Jersey Coast
Box Mississippi Valley
Box Herrings Fishermen
Box Out of the Fog
Box A Following Wind
Box Sunset In Iowa
Box Maine Woods
Box Misty Morning
Box Sunshine on the Florida Keys
Box Palms
Box Pintails
Box On Point
Box Grouse
Box Indian on a Bucking Horse
Box Peacocks
Box Roped
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: Papers, 1910-1966 and undated, and Artwork, circa 1920s-1960s. Each series is further arranged into subseries. Within the Papers series, folders within each subseries are arranged alphabetically, with the exception of deeds and other real estate documents, which are arranged according to the geographical distribution (north-south) of the properties they discuss. Most material within each folder is arranged chronologically.
Access Restrictions
Available for research.
Biographical Note
Frank Leonard Stick (10 February 1884-12 November 1966) was born in Huron, South Dakota, to David L Stick (1853-1914) and Lydia Jane Marcellus Stick (1852-1942). He had one brother, Daniel C. Stick (1879-1913). Frank Stick's family moved to Illinois in 1899, where he spent much of his time in the outdoors, hunting, fishing, and camping. He demonstrated a talent for art an early age. In his late teens, he moved to Chicago to study art and sold his first illustration to Sports Afield magazine when he was nineteen. He also studied under notable illustrator Howard Pyle in Wilmington, Delaware, for a time. His studies with Powell helped develop the specialized techniques he employed in the field of outdoor illustration. Stick soon made a career selling his paintings to sporting magazines and other publications, such as the Saturday Evening Post and Ladies Home Journal. Known for his paintings of dogs, Stick also produced illustrations for the short stories of Albert Payson Terhune and the Anti-Vivisection League of America.
In addition to his work as a painter, Stick was also an accomplished writer, and he contributed numerous editorial articles to Field and Stream and co-authored a book on surf fishing entitled The Call of the Surf. Throughout his life he wrote numerous vignettes, articles, and books on the topics of cancer prevention, beach erosion, fishing and hunting, ichthyology, and conservation, most of which remain unpublished.
Stick married Maud Hayes Stick in 1908, and the couple had two children: Charlotte Stick McMullan (1909-1969) and David Stick (1919-2009). In the early 1920s, with a group of other Howard Pyle students, Stick established an informal artists' colony in Interlaken, New Jersey, where he was elected the first mayor in 1922. A fishing trip in the mid-1920s brought him to the Outer Banks of North Carolina, where he became so enchanted with the area that he began buying up large tracts of property in Dare County. He retired from painting in 1929 and moved his family to the Skyco area of Roanoke Island. He then focused his career on real estate development and construction, and he became known for his modernist designs for simple flat top cottages. He was instrumental in the development of the communities of Virginia Dare Shores and Southern Shores. He co-founded several companies engaged in real estate development, including Kitty Hawk Development Company/Kitty Hawk Land Company, Southern Shores Realty Company, and Hatteras Holding Corporation.
Stick was an avid conservationist and spent much of his free time advocating for the preservation of the Outer Banks' natural resources. In 1933, Stick began to campaign for the establishment of a national park along the Outer Banks and began procuring extensive land holdings that would ultimately form the Cape Hatteras National Seashore. In establishing the park, one of Stick's goals was to protect and stabilize the area's fragile dunes, and he pioneered the design and construction of sand fences along the seashore, in addition to planting beach grasses for dune stabilization. He was also instrumental in bringing in transient and WPA work forces to engage in conservation work in the park. Stick was largely opposed to beach renourishment projects that involved bringing in sand, encouraging efforts to protect dunes as they stood rather than attempting to artificially extend the shoreline.
Stick returned to art in the early 1940s. His interest in ichthyology inspired the creation of nearly three hundred watercolor sketches of the fish he identified. He also drafted a book based on this work entitled Fishes of Atlantic and Caribbean Waters, which was never published. A revised version was eventually published under the title An Artist's Catch by his son, David, utilizing his famous fish watercolors as illustrations.
In his later life. Stick spent a great deal of his free time in the Florida Keys and the Virgin Islands. In the early 1950s, he began working closely with Laurance Rockefeller and other interested parties to acquire land holdings on the island of St. John, which were originally intended to be developed into a resort community. However, as Stick recalls in a 9 October 1960 letter to a business associate, Allston Boyer, "But one day as I sat on an out-cropping watching a bulldozer cut a red gash along the base of Old Bordeaux Mountain, visualization of what the future might bring came to me, and I determined then and there that this lovely island would not become a symbol of man's commercial desecration, if I could help it" (this letter can be found in the Correspondence, 1959-1963 folder of this collection, in the Virgin Islands National Park subseries of Stick's papers). Together Stick, Rockefeller, and several other property owners on the island worked to establish the Virgin Islands National Park in 1956.
Stick remained active as both a watercolorist and a realtor until the end of his life. He passed away in November 1966 in Dare County at the age of 82. He is buried alongside his wife and daughter in Austin Cemetery in Kitty Hawk, North Carolina.
Custodial History
Formerly classified as 33MSS-89, 33GRF-1, 33GRF-2, and 33GRF-11.
Acquisitions Information
The bulk of the collection was donated by David Stick or the David Stick Estate in various accessions, 1986-2011. Additional paintings were donated by Althea B. Adams, 1990, and Thomas A. McDonald, 2012.
David Stick Papers from Stick, David, 1919-2009,(collection 3012)
Maud Hayes Stick Papers from Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972,(collection 1013)
Collection Overview
The Frank Stick Papers and Artwork, 1910-1966 and undated, contains a substantial collection of artwork and personal papers created by Frank Stick. Included in the collection are Stick's fish watercolors, several of his landscape and naturalist oil paintings, papers related to his family and personal life, documentation of his efforts to establish the Cape Hatteras National Seashore and Virgin Islands National Park, numerous deeds and other real estate records documenting the early development of the Outer Banks, plans for his signature flat top cottages, drafts of his writings, and papers related to members of his immediate family. Much of his collection of personal papers consists of correspondence, in which he frequently remarks on the social and political conditions on the Outer Banks and throughout the nation, including civil rights and white supremacy, relations between privileged and underprivileged classes, modern colonization of native peoples in the Virgin Islands, and environmental conservation.
The collection is arranged into two series: Papers, 1910-1966 and undated, and Artwork, circa 1910s-1960s.
Other Finding Aids
A full index of Frank Stick's fish watercolors, including the dimensions of each piece and its matte and/or frame as well as the page on which it appears in An Artist's Catch, is available. Please contact the Outer Banks History Center for more details.
Stick, David, 1919-2009; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910
Cape Hatteras National Seashore (N.C.); United States--Works Progress Administration--North Carolina
Artists--New Jersey--Interlaken; Artists--North Carolina--Dare County; Ash Wednesday Storm, 1962; Beach Erosion--North Carolina; Coast changes--North Carolina; Conservation of natural resources; Ichthyology; Ichthyology--In art; Real estate development--North Carolina--Outer Banks; Shore Protection--North Carolina
Outer Banks (N.C.)--Environmental conditions; Outer Banks (N.C.)--History; Outer Banks (N.C.)--Race relations; United States Virgin Islands--Race relations; Virgin Islands National Park (United States Virgin Islands); Virginia Dare Shores (N.C.)
- Papers, 1910-1966 and undated; 45505; 0.020; Stick, Frank
  Scope and Content
  Frank Stick's papers document his business and personal interests, family life, and personal life. The bulk of the documents in this series date from the last two decades of Stick's life, but earlier materials are also included, particularly as related to Stick's efforts to establish the Cape Hatteras National Seashore and his real estate career. This series is divided into four subseries: Conservation, 1931-1966 and undated; Writings, 1924-1965 and undated; Professional Papers, 1922-1966 and undated; and Personal Papers, 1910-1966 and undated.
  - Conservation, 1931-1966 and undated; 7941; 0.010; Stick, Frank
    The Conservation subseries contains material related to Frank Stick's various conservation interests and the initiatives in which he participated. Most of the materials in this series relate to Stick's work to establish national parks on North Carolina's Outer Banks (the Cape Hatteras National Seashore) and the island of St. John (Virgin Islands National Park), but documentation of Stick's interest in erosion control and wildlife conservation, as well as papers related to various projects in the state of Florida in which he was interested are included. The bulk of the material is correspondence, but maps, reports and other publications, legal documents, and clippings are also included.
    - Cape Hatteras National Seashore, 1935-1963; 7942; Stick, Frank
      The Cape Hatteras National Seashore subseries, 1935-1963, contains materials documenting Frank Stick's attempts to establish a national park on the Outer Banks south of Oregon Inlet. Papers primarily consist of correspondence, largely written or received by Frank Stick, relating to land acquisition, lobbying efforts, conservation measures, and project planning. Several letters in this subseries document the complicated social history of the park, such as local opposition to the establishment of an African American Civilian Conservation Corps camp and concerns about the "transient class" representing the Works Progress Administration's labor base. In addition to correspondence, drafts and published copies of legislation, maps, and isolated records of the Cape Hatteras National Seashore Commission are also included.
      - Cape Hatteras National Seashore Commission, 1940; 30877; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
        This folder primarily consists of letters written by Frank Stick, in his capacity as secretary of the commission, to R. Bruce Etheridge and other representatives with an interest in the Cape Hatteras National Seashore. Many of Stick's letters express his discomfort that the language of the proposed bill to establish the park would result in overhunting of waterfowl, while others discuss work done to recruit donations and survey land holdings on Ocracoke to be included in the park. In a 24 June 1940 letter to Etheridge, Stick describes "the old negro, Bryant, head of the only colored family on Ocracoke Island" who wished to contribute his land to the project. Stick remarks that "here is some darned good publicity if properly handled." In addition to correspondence, the folder includes typed transcripts of data related to the commission (such as budgetary and membership information), drafts and published copies of bills and amendments, and a map of the area covered by the project.
      - Correspondence, 1952-1958; 30878; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
        This folder primarily consists of letters sent to or from Representative Herbert C. Bonner and National Park Service Director Conrad L. Wirth, as well as letters related to erosion control and other conservation efforts explored during the Cape Hatteras National Seashore project.
      - Hatteras Holding Corporation Donation to National Park Service, 1950-1953; 30879; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
      - National Park Service Correspondence, 1953-1955; 30880; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
      - Phipps Tract, 1954-1955; 30881; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
      - State Park Plan, 1935; 30882; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
        These materials comprise correspondence between Frank Stick, State and National Park Service personnel, and prospective property donors regarding establishing a state park in the area now known as the Cape Hatteras National Seashore. Many of the letters are from John S. Phipps, who owned a 4,000-acre tract of land on Hatteras Island, including the J.D. Dailey Tract desired by the National Park Service for the park. The establishment of a state park on Hatteras Island was viewed by project organizers as a precursory step to creating a national park there.
        Many of the letters in this folder discuss protective measures to be taken to guard the seashore from erosion and the establishment of a Civilian Conservation Corps (CCC) camp to assist with this work, including some discussion pertinent to race relations in the area. In a 17 June 1935 letter, Stick remarks that "While a negro CCC camp would probably do as much work as a white camp, we feel that it should not be established on the banks...I believe I can say with complete confidence that a negro camp will not be placed in the Hatteras area." Establishment of a camp was denied in June 1935, possibly (according to Stick) due to concerns over whether it would be staffed by African American workmen.
      - United States of America vs. Certain Lands on Hatteras Island…, 1963; 30883; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
      - Works Progress Administration (WPA), 1935-1936; 30884; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
        This folder consists of correspondence related to the use of Works Progress Administration (WPA) laborers in creating the Cape Hatteras National Seashore. Letters primarily discuss the supervisory responsibility associated with bringing in WPA workers and the general oversight of the project. In his letters, Stick expresses concern with the lack of qualified leaders allocated to oversee the unskilled laborers hired by the WPA, stating in one letter (9 January 1936), "...no class is more dependent upon leadership impossible to provide from the Transient class."
    - Erosion Control, 1956-1966; 30885; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
    - Florida Projects, 1957-1960; 7943; Stick, Frank
      - Everglades National Park, 1957-1960; 30886; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
      - Fort Jefferson National Monument, 1959-1960; 30887; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
      - Key West Deer Bill, 1957-1958; 30888; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
    - Henry C. Phipps Property (Near Wright Memorial), 1935; 30889; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
    - Virgin Islands National Park, 1932-1963 and undated (bulk 1952-1959); 1952-1959; 7944; 0.010; Stick, Frank
      The Virgin Islands National Park subseries, 1932-1963 and undated (bulk 1952-1959) contains materials created or collected by Frank Stick over the course of his campaign to establish a national park on the island of St. John in the U.S. Virgin Islands. Most of this subseries consists of correspondence, but brochures, event programs, reports, maps, publications, clippings, and legal documents are also included. Much of the correspondence is between Frank Stick and Allston Boyer, an associate of the Rockefellers, resort planner, and conservationist who helped develop several national parks in addition to Virgin Islands National Park. Letters to National Park Service superintendent Conrad Wirth, letters from Stick to various government officials, and correspondence between Stick and property owners who sold land acquired for the park are also included. Additionally, many of the letters in this subseries related to the operations of the Lameshur estate, a property purchased by Laurance Rockefeller with the intention of establishing a park and managed by the Stick family. Drafts of articles written by Stick on St. John and the Virgin Islands National Park can be found in the Writings series.
      - Brochures and Catalogues, 1932-1956 and undated; 30890; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
      - Cherney, Paul (Submarine Research Institute, Cannes, France), 1954; 30891; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
      - Clippings, 1954-1959; 30892; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
      - Contracts and Options, 1954-1956; 30893; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 1952-1956; 30894; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 1957; 30895; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1958; 30896; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1959-1963; 30897; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - Correspondence: Ridge and Linda Folk, 1953, 1957; 30898; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
        Letters primarily discuss a heated dispute between the Folks and Frank Faulk, owner of the Reef Bay estate on St. John, for which the Folks served as caretakers until May 1953. Following the dispute, the Folks moved to the adjacent Lameshur Estate where they were retained by Stick as caretakers. The letters discuss improvements made to both properties and the daily tasks of the Folks as they carried out their duties on St. John.
      - Draft of Letter to Governor Archie Alexander, 10 May 1954; 30899; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - Government House, 1955; 30900; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - Hubler, Hal, 1954-1956; 30901; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - International Park, 1957-1958; 30902; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - Jackson Hole Preserve, 1954-1956; 30903; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - Joshua, Clodina, 1954-1955; 30904; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - Lameshur Accounts, 1954-1955; 30905; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - Maps and Plats, 1934-1959 and undated; 38800; 0.010; Stick, Frank (Folder Oversize Folder 2)
      - National Geographic, 1955; 30906; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - National Park Service, 1954-1960 and undated; 30907; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - Notes, 1954 and undated; 30908; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - Reports and Articles, 1953; 30909; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
        This folder includes a published copy of Senate Bill 1604 authorizing the establishment of Virgin Islands National Park.
      - Reports and Event Programs, 1955-1957; 30910; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 2)
      - St. John Land Co. - Lameshur, 1955-1957; 30911; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
      - St. John Plan and Review of Letters, 1957-1959; 30912; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
      - St. John Plan, Rockefeller, 1958; 30913; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
    - Wildlife Conservation, 1931, 1958; 30914; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
  - Writings, 1924-1965 and undated; 7945; Stick, Frank
    The Writings series, 1924-1965 and undated, contains drafts and manuscript fragments, correspondence, clippings, and research material related to Stick's various writing projects. Stick's writings primarily relate to his interests in ichthyology and conservation, but other topics are also covered. The series is arranged into two subseries: Ichthyology, 1950-1965 and undated; and Articles and Other Writings, 1924-1963 and undated. Most of the undated material likely dates from the latter part of Stick's life, circa 1950s-1960s.
    - Ichthyology, 1950-1965 and undated; 7946; Stick, Frank
      The Ichthyology subseries, 1950-1965 and undated, contains drafts and research materials related to Stick's study of ichthyology. Particularly, much of the material in this subseries relates to Stick's book, Fishes of Atlantic and Caribbean Waters, which was never published, despite several publishers expressing interest in it. Included in this series is correspondence between Stick and publishers, scholars, ichthyologists, and other individuals interested in the study of fish; drafts of Stick's book and other writings on fish; and research materials. Drafts are undated, but likely date from the mid-1950s. Related to Stick's study of ichthyology are his watercolor paintings of fish, which can be found in the Artwork series of this collection.
      - Cairns, Huntington, 1951-1965; 30915; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
      - Coates, C.W. (Curator, New York Aquarium), 1956; 30916; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1950-1965; 30917; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
      - Correspondence: Fish Book, 1950-1960; 30918; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
      - Correspondence with Publishers, 1956; 30919; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
      - Fishes of Atlantic and Caribbean Waters, undated; 7947; Stick, Frank
        - Draft, undated; 30920; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
        - Draft, Barracudas, undated; 30921; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
        - Draft, Chapter 1, undated; 30922; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
        - Draft, Foreword, undated; 30923; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
        - Draft Fragments, undated; 30924; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
        - Draft, Herring-Like Fishes, undated; 30925; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
        - Draft, Rockfish, undated; 30926; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
        - Draft, Sharks, Man-O-War Fish, etc., undated; 30927; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 3)
        - Lists of Fishes, undated; 30928; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 4)
        - Suggested Subjects and Chapter Headings, undated; 30929; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 4)
      - Fishin' Round the Virgin Islands, undated; 30930; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 4)
      - Ginsberg, Dr. Isaac, 1954-1956; 30931; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 4)
      - Griswold, Oliver, 1954; 30932; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 4)
      - Hale Publishing Company, 1951-1952; 30933; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 4)
      - Information on Fish, 1951-1959 and undated; 30934; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 4)
      - Kidd, Alan, 1960-1961; 30935; Stick, Frank (Folder Box 4)